Ivan Palmegiani, MSc

ivan.palmegiani@gmail.com | LinkedIn Account | GitHub Account

Personal address and phone number available on request



Profile

Environmental researcher with cross-disciplinary expertise including natural sciences, landscape ecology as well as geographic information systems (GIS), data analytic, and machine learning (ML). Capable of communicating data and analysis results in spoken, written and visual form. Earth Observation enthusiast. OpenStreetMap contributor. Proponent of nature-based solutions for climate change adaptation and mitigation. Team player, also able to take charge of tasks individually. Constructive critical thinker. Solution oriented and careful about details. Strong analytical mindset and excellent organization skills. Highly motivated and positive towards challenges. Moved by inherent curiosity and engaged in continuous learning.

Technical expertise

Advanced QGIS | Geospatial Analysis and Remote Sensing in Python | R Statistical Computing | Multi-Dimensional Data Visualization - Grammar of Graphics | Data Reporting in R-Markdown and Jupyter notebooks | Geodatabase Management in PostgreSQL-PostGIS | Command Line Interface Tools in Linux | Version Control in Git & GitHub | Conda Environments | Containerization in Docker | Fundamentals of Web-GIS Development

Languages

English - IELTS certification level C1 • German - TELC certification level B1 • Italian - mother tongue • Spanish - fluent • Portuguese - fluent

Professional Experience

Climate Co-Adaptation Lab Fellow at PlanAdapt

Fellowship, since Apr. 2021

Proposal development for climate change adaptation with a focus on GIS and EO technologies in sustainable agricultural development.

External Geospatial Data Consultant at WWF Water Risk Filter

Contract, Feb. 2021 - ongoing

Working closely with the technical project manager, I review protocols and methodologies to analyze corporate water risk data, design data visualizations and global water risk maps to support corporate partners in their path towards Water Stewardship. I'm in charge for the automation of data analysis and reporting workflows.

Tech stack: R GIS packages, Rstudio, R-Plotly, Conda, Git & GitHub.

External Geospatial Data Scientist at SmartCloudFarming GmbH

Contract, Mar. 2020 - Feb. 2021

Research and development in a production context: following the principles of agile development, I have coordinated a small team of data professionals and personally worked at the development of a minimum viable product (MVP) for the estimation of water content in agricultural soil.

Performed literature research to identify state-of-the-art methods for the estimation of soil water content and soil

organic carbon from satellite imagery

- Presented key findings in bibliographical reports
- Identified suitable data sources to facilitate programmatic access to satellite imagery, and to ground data
- Developed data science pipelines to source and composite satellite imagery to train machine learning (ML) models, and prepared ground data to test and validate predictions
- Co-developed and fine-tuned ML models to predict soil moisture content from satellite data. The accuracy of predictions is satisfactory (R squared > 0.95, RMSE < 0.05)
- Generated interactive data visualizations and 3D maps to report model predictions to executives
- Developed dashboards to display ground data and model predictions to investors, and to potential clients

Tech stack: Python GIS libraries, QGIS, sklearn, Python-Plotly, Streamlit, Conda, Docker, PostgreSQL-PostGIS, Google Earth Engine, Google Cloud Platform, Google App Engine

External Data Consultant at Earth Ratings UG

Contract, Jan. 2020 - Jun. 2020

Explored CDP data and methodologies | Identified and sourced additional data sets on Corporate Environmental Footprint (CEF) and Social Responsibility (CSR) | Developed a web scraper program to source publicly available data in accordance with the respective terms of use | Converted raw contents to tabular formats and integration of open data sets from several sources | Exploratory analyses and visualization of the resulting data sets

Tech stack: web scarping and data munging was performed in Python

External Data Management Consultant at University of Primorska

Contract, Jan. 2020

The role implied the revision of data storage procedures at the Conservation and Population Genetic research group. The tasks included cleansing of genetic data sets and migration from data sheets to database tables, development of functional solutions for data storage in relational databases, automating data querying, and advising the research team on wildlife data management. The work has been conduced using open-source software for data cleansing and manipulation, while proprietary database solutions (Microsoft Access) have been used for data storage.

Tech stack: data munging in Python, user interfaces for data entry were generated with Microsoft Access

Professional re-qualification

Oct. 2018 - Nov. 2019

Data Science and Python programming courses | German language course | Conflict management and non-violent-communication (NVC) self-training | Personal development

Graduate Research Assistant at Leibniz Institute for Zoo and Wildlife Research

Full-time, Apr. 2013 - Jun. 2018

Evolutionary ecology studies of the cheetah in central Namibia with particular focus on the mating system

Desk research activities:

- Development of data collection protocols and field project management
- Planning and supervising field campaigns for the live-capture of cheetahs
- Spatial and movement analyses of GPS-telemetry data
- Modeling distribution of the species and its use of space
- · Modeling individual movement patterns and interactions
- Data management in Movebank
- Design and maintenance of PostgreSQL-PostGIS database
- Hypothesis testing
- Presenting scientific results to the general public through talks, data visualizations and reports
- Organization of scientific symposia

Field activities:

Executing live-capture campaigns of cheetahs using custom-build box traps

- Assisting in the live-capture of leopards using custom-build box traps
- Collected and analyzed presence-absence data via camera-trap surveys
- Engaged with local communities and stakeholders for the mitigating human-wildlife conflict
- Coordinated data collection in the field, supervised technicians and volunteers

Education

Master of Science (MSc), Jul. 2010

Environmental Sciences and Natural Resources Management, University of Sassari.

Grade: 110/110 Summa cum Laude

Systems ecology, landscape ecology, regional geology, pedology, sedimentology, wildlife conservation and management, conservation genetics, environmental modelling, statistical inference, advanced statistical theory, environmental economics

Training courses - Selected

Advanced QGIS with Official Certification, Sept 2021

Spatial Thoughts

Modeling and Automating GIS Workflows | Visualizing Time Series and 3D Data | Advanced Expressions

ARSET - Species Distribution Modeling with Remote Sensing, Aug. 2021

Applied Remote Sensing Training Program, NASA

Overview of Species Distribution Models (SDMs) | Data Sources for Species Distribution and Remote Sensing Data for Landscape Characterization | Tools for conducting SDM for a variety of ecosystems such Wallace R-based platform for modeling of species niches and distributions

Copernicus MOOC, Sept. 2020 - Dec. 2020

Copernicus programme, from European Union and European Space Agency

Overview on the programme | Copernicus data and services | Renewable Energy | Security and Emergency Management | Resource Management | Land Use and Management | Air quality, water pollution and ecosystem health monitoring | Integrating Copernicus data with other sources: Machine Learning, Al | Ideation | Prototyping | Developing | Collaboration

Echoes in Space, July 2020

EO College, European Space Agency - Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena

History of Radar technology and the discovery of electromagnetic waves | Image acquisition | Geometry of airborne and space borne Radar systems | Land applications of Radar remote sensing | Applications of radar remote sensing over Water | Application of Radar remote sensing for Hazard management

Data Science Bootcamp, Aug. 2019 - Nov. 2019

Business Trends Academy

Data protection and ethical matters | Linear and nonlinear regression | A/B testing | Hypothesis testing | Data visualization in Tableau | Object oriented programming (OOP) | Python modules and functions | Pandas and NumPy | Multiprocessing and multithreading | RESTful API | Webscraping | Neural Networks and Machine Learning techniques | Keras and TensorFlow

Hobbies and interests

Cooking • Indoor gardening • Outdoor sports and activities such as climbing, bouldering, hiking, biking, canoeing, camping • Tai Chi • DIY and Handicraft • Music and Arts • Urban agriculture